Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ב, Lamed Beis,
שבועות Shavuos 30, and we pick up with the משנה mishnah on
the bottom or the bottom third of ל"א עמוד ב', Lamed Aleph
Amud Beis, and we are sort of moving from discussing the parameters
and criteria of שבועת העדות Shvuos Ha'eidus to the actual scenario of
how it actually plays out. So let's take a look. משנה. Mishnah.
שבועת העדות כיצד? Shvuos Ha'eidus keitzad? So what is the circumstances which
generates a שבועת העדות Shvuos Ha'eidus or that you have a שבועת
העדות Shvuos Ha'eidus that obligates a קרבן? korban? אמר לשנים בואו והעידוני,
Amar lishnayim bo vehiduni, so somebody comes to two people who have
to be כשר לעדות kasher l'eidus and says come and bring testimony
for me and it requires that he be talking to two עדים
eidim and not just one עד eid because the understanding is that
שבועת העדות Shvuos Ha'eidus you're only חייב chayav if it was a
type of an עדות eidus that could be used
to win the case, to extract ממון. mamon. So he says to
two come and testify in my behalf.
שבועה שאין אנו יודעים לך עדות Shvuah she'ein anu yod'im lacha eidus
and they say, they take an oath, we don't know any testimony
on your behalf and they're lying, so that would be the scenario
of a שבועת העדות Shvuos Ha'eidus that you bring a קרבן. korban.
או שאמרו לו אין אנו יודעים לך עדות, O she'amru lo ein
anu yod'im lacha eidus, so they didn't say a שבועה, shvuah, they
just said we don't know any testimony, and then he says משביע
אני עליכם, mashpia ani aleichem, I am impose a שבועה shvuah on
you, I call upon you to take an oath that you do
not know testimony on my behalf, ואמרו אמן, v'amru amen, and they
said yes, they said אמן. amen. הרי אלו חייבים, Harei elu chayavim,
they're חייבים. chayavim.
Now, that second case sounds like מושבע מפי אחרים, mushpa mipi acherim,
if you'll remember there was a whole discussion about מושבע מפי עצמו,
mushpa mipi atzmo, מושבע מפי אחרים, mushpa mipi acherim, is מושבע מפי
אחרים mushpa mipi acherim only in בית דין beis din and so
on, but actually because the person said אמן amen and the הלכה
halacha is that כל האומר אמן כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי, kol ha'omer
amen k'motzi shvuah mipiv dami, so the saying of אמן amen is
like the person themselves said the word שבועה shvuah that I don't
know עדות. eidus. So both of these are actually scenarios about מושבע
מפי עצמו. mushpa mipi atzmo. מושבע מפי אחרים mushpa mipi acherim would
be that the person would say משביע אני עליכם mashpia ani aleichem
that you don't know עדות eidus and they would say we're telling
you we don't know עדות. eidus. So they did not take the
שבועה shvuah but they were standing by their position after he placed
the שבועה shvuah on them. Okay, but our משנה mishnah anyways two
scenarios of which they are basically taking a שבועה shvuah they don't
know עדות. eidus. הרי אלו חייבים Harei elu chayavim and they're lying
then they're חייבים. chayavim. Now, השביע עליהם חמשה פעמים חוץ לבית דין
ובאו לבית דין והודו פטורין. hispia aleihem chamishah pe'amim chutz labeis din
uvau labeis din vehodu p'turin. So if he took made them take
the oath even five times outside of בית דין beis din and
then when they came to בית דין beis din they actually admitted
that they do know testimony they're exempt, because the גמרא Gemara will
see
that we'll learn it out for sort of there's two aspects here.
One is based on a פסוק pasuk they understand that אם לוא
יגיד im lo yagid that it has to be in a context
where they could give their testimony, so it has to be in
the בית דין beis din itself although the שבועה shvuah doesn't have
to be in the בית דין beis din but at least the
denial of the עדות eidus has to be in the בית דין.
beis din. And the other point to be made here is that
as long as they are claiming they don't know outside of בית
דין beis din they're not testifying they don't know. So they always
have the ability to retract and therefore the issue is still a
live one and they could testify when they get to בית דין.
beis din. Whereas if they take once they take a שבועה shvuah
in בית דין beis din then or deny that they know the
testimony in בית דין beis din they can't retract it which we
will see coming up that's principle of כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר
ומגיד. kivan she'higid shuv eino chozer umaggid. Alright, so again if he
makes them take an oath outside of בית דין beis din they're
not חייב chayav until they actually and even if they're lying and
they deny knowledge they're not going to be חייב chayav until they
deny in בית דין beis din itself.
Now, השביע עליהם חמשה פעמים חוץ לבית דין, hispia aleihem chamishah pe'amim
chutz labeis din, let's say he does this, makes them five times
he says משביע אני עליכם mashpia ani aleichem or they say שבועה
שאין אנו יודעים shvuah she'ein anu yod'im and then let me just
read that. השביע חמשה פעמים חוץ לבית דין ובאו לבית דין והודו
פטורין. hispia chamishah pe'amim chutz labeis din uvau labeis din vehodu p'turin.
So then they admit they're פטור. patur. So if they admit in
בית דין. beis din. כפרו חייבים על כל אחת ואחת. Kafru chayavim
al kol achas v'achas. If they come to בית דין beis din
and when they're in בית דין beis din they deny, so here
their denial really has traction because they're denying in a place where
they could give עדות eidus and כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד,
kivan she'higid shuv eino chozer umaggid, so that denial sort of gives
the force to the שבועות shvuos that preceded. And since there were
five שבועות shvuot that preceded they are actually five קרבנות. korbanot. We
learn from a פסוק pasuk that you could be חייב chayav on
each and every שבועה. shvuah. Okay, so it's an interesting הלכה halacha
that every separate שבועה shvuah you should be חייב chayav for, but
it only gets triggered or only becomes a meaningful שבועה shvuah once
there is a denial כפירה kfirah in בית
דין.
beis din.
Continuing on. השביע עליהם חמשה פעמים לפני בית דין. Hispia aleihem chamishah
pe'amim lifnei beis din.
Now let's say everything took place in front of בית דין. beis
din. Five times he said משביע אני עליכם mashpia ani aleichem they
said אמן amen in the presence of בית דין. beis din. So
you would think this time definitely they bring five קרבנות korbanos everything
is in בית דין. beis din. But no. וכפרו אינם חייבים אלא
אחת, Vekafru einam chayavim ela achas, they're only חייב chayav one קרבן.
korban. Why? So אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, מה טעם, ma
ta'am, what's the reason? הואיל ואינם יכולים לחזור להודות ho'il ve'einam yecholim
lachzor lehodos because once they make the first denial in בית דין,
Beis Din, it's כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד. keivan shehigid shuv
eino chozer u'maggid. Once you testify or claim you don't know testimony,
you cannot retract in the presence of בית דין, Beis Din, you
cannot retract that and then give testimony. So from the moment they
did their first כפירה kfira in בית דין, Beis Din, every other
שבועה shvua was not a שבועת העדות. shvuas eidus. It wouldn't matter
if they knew or they didn't know. They're not in a position
to testify. It's like they're פסולי עדות psulei eidus after they first
claim that they don't know in בית דין. Beis Din. All right,
so once there's a כפירה kfira in בית דין, Beis Din, that
triggers the חיוב, chiyuv, but it also prevents any other חיוב chiyuv
for a שבועה shvua that would follow. Okay,
now we're moving on to the idea that there are two עדים
eidim and how does it work that both of them are חייב?
chayav? So,
or are they always both חייב? chayav? So the משנה mishna says
like this: כפרו שניהם כאחד שניהם חייבות. kafru sheneihem k'echad sheneihem chayavos.
Both of them at the same time say אין אני יודע לך
עדות ein ani yodeia lecha eidus or שבועה אין אני יודע לך
עדות shvua ein ani yodeia lecha eidus or אמן amen at the
same time, then they're both חייב. chayav. Okay, they both did the
act of taking the false שבועת העדות shvuas eidus in a context
in which they could have been מעיד maeid and helped the guy
in his court case. However, זה אחר זה הראשון חייב והשני פטור.
zeh achar zeh harishon chayav vehasheni patur. If it is sequential, when
the first one says I don't know עדות, eidus, then he's in
a position that his testimony could join with the second guy's and
could actually, you know, support the case of this of the בעל
דין ba'al din and therefore he is withholding this valuable עדות, eidus,
so he's חייב. chayav. But the second guy, once the first guy
did his כפירה kfira and we've seen that the he's only חייב
chayav once the כפירה kfira takes place in בית דין, Beis Din,
so once the first guy denies and the first guy's not in
a position now to testify at all, the second person is only
an עד אחד. ed echad. So the second person's cannot really help
this guy fully win his case. So the second person is not
חייב chayav for the שבועת העדות. shvuas eidus. השני פטור. hasheni patur.
Okay, כפר אחד והודה אחד הכופר חייב. kafar echad vehodeh echad hakofair
chayav. And not only that, or I don't know, maybe this is
obvious, if the first guy denies and then the second guy says
yes I do know עדות, eidus, so the first guy is חייב.
chayav. Maybe that's obvious from the previous one. The first guy held
back עדות eidus that could help and the second one was even
willing to testify, you know, truthfully. היו שתי כיתי עדים. hayu shtei
kitei eidim.
So now let's say there are two groups of עדים eidim and
he goes to like all four people or the two groups of
two. So כפרו הראשונה ואחר כך כפרו השניה שתיהן חייבות. kafru harishona
ve'achar kach kafru hashniya shteihen chayavos.
So two groups of עדים eidim is different than two individuals, because
here even after the first group of עדים eidim denied and they
were not in a position to retract, the second group of עדים
eidim could still bring their testimony if both of the second group
testified the guy would win. So therefore the חיוב chiyuv can still
be on the second group. שתיהן חייבות מפני שהעדות יכולה להתקיים בשתיהן
shteihen chayavos mipnei shehaeidus yechola lehiskayem bishteihen
because even after the each one of those groups is sufficient to
establish the עדות eidus on behalf of this person. All right, so
let's take a look now at the גמרא Gemara as it unpacks
each piece of this. אמר שמואל. amar Shmuel. So Shmuel's going to
start with a piece that isn't even in the משנה. mishna. ראוהו
שרץ אחריהם. ra'uhu sheratz achareihem.
They see the litigant, the בעל דין ba'al din running after them.
He say, "Wait, wait, wait, I need you, I need you." Okay,
אמרו לו מה תרץ אחרינו? amru lo ma tatz achareinu? And they
say, "Why are you running after us? שבועה שאיננו יודעים לך עדות.
shvua she'einanu yod'im lecha eidus. We know you're planning on asking us
to testify; we are taking a שבועה shvua that we don't know
any testimony on your behalf." פטורין. pturan. They're exempt. Why if they're
lying? עד שישמעו מפיו. ad sheyishme'u mipi.
Because of a criteria not said explicitly in the משנה. mishna. The
משנה mishna described the scenario but it didn't explicitly point out that
they have to hear directly from him that he is demanding from
them to come and testify in his behalf. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. מאי קמשמע לן שמואל? mai kamashma lan Shmuel?
What are you telling us? תנינא. tanina. We actually already learned this,
or rather we didn't already learn it but we're going to learn
it. It's a משנה mishna that's coming up. שלח ביד עבדו או
שאמר להן הנתבע משביעני עליכם שאם אתם יודעים לו עדות שתבואו ותעידוהו.
shalach beyad avdo o she'amar lahen hanitba mashpiani aleichem she'im atem yod'im
lo
eidus shetavo vet'iduho. So let's say the litigant who needed their testimony
sent his servant or his agent to go demand from them that
they come and testify. Or let's say even the other side, you
know, he was a really honest guy, so the guy that was
being sued let's say said to the עדים, eidim, "I am imposing
a שבועה shvua on you that if you know for any evidence
on behalf of the person who is suing me that you should
go and testify in his behalf."
So they're being called on to testify but not from the person
who needs their testimony directly. הרי אלו פטורין. harei elu pturin. And
the משנה mishna says they're exempt. Why? עד שישמעו מפי התובע. ad
sheyishme'u mipi hatoveia. Because they have to hear the demand from the
person who needs their testimony. We'll see in a minute where we
get where we get this from how or when we get later
to the משנה, mishna, you know, which פסוקים pesukim this is based
on. So anyway, so we already know that הלכה halacha that they
have to... So you have to hear from him, so what's the
חידוש chiddush of שמואל? Shmuel? And the גמרא Gemara says what is
pretty clear what the חידוש chiddush of שמואל Shmuel is. The גמרא
Gemara says: רץ אחריהן איצטריכא ליה. ratz achareihen itztricha lei. No, no,
no, there's a big difference between having somebody else go and you
yourself are going but you just haven't yet articulated the words. Because
now you could almost say like you're implicitly by your running and
it's clear from context why you're running, that is an implicit demand.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitakh amina, I might have thought, כיון דרץ
אחריהן כמאן דאמר להו דמי, kivan de-ratz achareihen ke-man de-amar lehu dami,
if since you're running after them and again given the right context,
it's like he's making the demand directly from them, קא משמע לן.
ka mashma lan. So that's what שמואל Shmuel is telling us, that
doesn't count, they have to really hear him say it. So the
גמרא Gemara says, והא נמי תנינא, ve-ha nami tanina, but one minute,
we already learned that in a coming up משנה. mishna. Why? Because
it says the following: שבועת העדות כיצד, shvuas haeidut keitzad, or excuse
me, our משנה. mishna. We already learned that in our משנה. mishna.
שבועת העדות כיצד, shvuas haeidut keitzad, אמר לעדים בואו והעידוני שבועה וכולי,
amar l'eidim bo'u v'heiduni shvuah v'khulei, etc. אמר, amar,
so our משנה mishna when it describes the classic scenario, it has
him saying directly, verbally, come and testify on my behalf. Now of
course our משנה's mishna not defining the criteria, it's just describing the
classic scenario, but the גמרא's Gemara saying we could have inferred from
our משנה mishna that you needed it to be verbal. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר אין לא אמר לא, amar in lo amar
lo, so only if he verbalizes it, if he didn't verbalize it,
not. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אמר לאו דוקא. amar lav
davka. No, the משנה, mishna, it's not really saying that that's a
requirement. It's giving a classic scenario, he said. But even if he
communicated it without words, that also could work. I might have thought
that, and שמואל Shmuel is coming to tell us that's not the
case. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי לא תימא הכי, v'i lo
teima hakhi, and I'll prove to you that אמר amar in the
משנה mishna is not a requirement or could be read as not
a requirement. ואי לא תימא הכי, v'i lo teima hakhi, גבי פיקדון
דקתני, gabei pikadon de-katni, when we're dealing when it comes to שבועת
הפיקדון, shvuas hapikadon, the משנה mishna says: שבועת הפיקדון כיצד, shvuas hapikadon
keitzad,
what's the scenario of a שבועת הפיקדון shvuas hapikadon when somebody takes
a שבועה shvuah denying that he's holding property of another person? אמר
לו תן לי פיקדון שיש לי בידך, amar lo ten li pikadon
she-yesh li b'yadkha, give me my, the thing I gave you to
watch on my behalf. So, and we know that the הלכה halacha
is, or we're going to find out the הלכה halacha is, that
you don't need a direct verbal תביעה tviah demand from the person
for שבועת הפיקדון. shvuas hapikadon. That's only a requirement for שבועת העדות.
shvuas haeidut. And nevertheless, the description it gives is that he verbalizes
and makes the demand. הכא נמי זו היא, hakha nami zo hi,
you think that אמר amar always means דוקא, davka, always means a
real requirement? אמר אין לא אמר לא? amar in lo amar lo?
So that's what, so we do really claim that? That by even
שבועת הפיקדון shvuas hapikadon they have to verbally hear him demand it?
והכחיש בעמיתו כתיב, ve-hikhash be-amito ktiv,
it says that you deny your friend and it doesn't give a
context, right,
by the שבועת העדות shvuas haeidut it says ושמעה קול אלה, ve-sham-ah
kol alah, he hears an oath being imposed on him. But by
שבועת הפיקדון, shvuas hapikadon, it just says he denies, he rejects any
obligation to his fellow.
So כולהו, kulhu,
any form in which he's going to take a false שבועה shvuah
about his responsibility by שבועת הפיקדון shvuas hapikadon he's חייב. chayav. So
what do we see? We see from the description by שבועת הפיקדון
shvuas hapikadon it has the guy saying, give me back my object,
but that's just a classic scenario, that's not a requirement. So I
could have thought from our משנה mishna as well, it's just a
classic scenario and not a requirement. And therefore שמואל Shmuel had to
come and say I want to make it clear that verbalizing it
is a requirement. The גמרא Gemara is still not satisfied. The גמרא
Gemara says הי מאי? hei mai? What are you, how can you
be saying this? אי אמרת בשלמא אמר דהכא דוקא תנא התם אטו
הכא. i amrat bishlama amar de-hakha davka tana hatam atu hakha.
It says I could explain very simply, the way I would have
read it, says the גמרא, Gemara, is when you start with שבועת
העדות, shvuas haeidut, you say he said, and that actually is required,
and that's the normal way I would have read it. And then
when it gets to שבועת פיקדון, shvuas pikadon, it patterns the description
similar to שבועת העדות shvuas haeidut and it uses the word אמר
amar again even though in that case it's not required. That would
have made sense, but that we're introducing the word here because it's
required and then we keep on using it. Okay, and then I
wouldn't need שמואל Shmuel to tell me anything because I would have
figured it out from our משנה. mishna. But in your scenario, אלא
אי אמרת לא אמר דהתם דוקא ולא אמר דהכא דוקא,
ela i amrat lo amar
de-hatam davka ve-lo amar de-hakha davka,
but if you say both in our scenario and in the scenario
by שבועת פיקדון shvuas pikadon it's just, you don't really need the
guy to say anything, so if that's true, אמר אמר למה לי
למיתני? amar amar lama li le-misnei?
Why is it constantly giving a scenario of he said, he said,
he said, if in no circumstance is that really
required? Therefore the Gemara says I really did not need Shmuel's teaching.
I could have figured out that it does actually need to be
verbal. All right, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara response responds.
No, דילמא אורחא דמילתא קא משמע לן.
dilma orcha demilsa ka
mashma lan.
So דילמא אורחא דמילתא, dilma orcha demilsa,
don't be such a literalist. Don't have to read every single word
as specifying a הלכה halacha criteria. It could be that in both
cases it said the guy said and it was just giving a
classic scenario but it actually was never a requirement. All right, so
the משניות Mishnayos are trying to illustrate for you what a classic
scenario looks like, but I actually could have read both cases of
the guy saying as not ever really being required and I could
have thought that by שבועת העדות Shevuas Ha'eidus even a non-verbal demand
would have sufficed. קא משמע לן kamashma lan and that's what Shmuel
is coming to tell us. Shmuel is coming to tell us that
actually verbalized demand is required by שבועת העדות. Shevuas Ha'eidus. Okay, תניא
כוותיה דשמואל, tanya k'vasei de'shmuel, we taught like Shmuel. והוא שבא אחריהם,
ve'hu sheba achareihem, they saw the guy coming after them. אמרו לו
מה אתה בא אחרינו שבועה שאין אנו יודעים לך עדות פטורים. amru
lo ma ata ba achareinu shevua she'ein anu yodim lach eidus paturim.
So exactly almost word for word what Shmuel said. So they see
running after, they take the שבועה, shevua, they're exempt because they did
not hear him verbally demand it. ואם בפקדון חייבין. ve'im be'pikadon chayavin.
But if it were a case by פקדון, pikadon, they would be
חייבין chayavin because as we saw by פקדון pikadon you do not
have the same requirements of hearing it directly from the person making
the demand. Okay, very good. So that's the first part of our
משנה mishna to tell us that the אמר amar is דווקא davka
and to introduce us the גמרא, Gemara, the idea we're going to
find out later on that they have to hear it directly from
the תובע. toveia.
Now we get to the actual taking apart the pieces of the
משנה. mishna. Okay, השביע עליהם חמשה פעמים. hishpia aleihem chamisha pe'amim.
So this is the case where they took five oaths outside of
בית דין Beis Din and if they admit when they get to
בית דין Beis Din they're going to be פטור. patur. You need
the denial in בית דין Beis Din to trigger the חיוב chiyuv
of the שבועה. shevua. But when they do take that, that denial,
they're חייב chayav five times. Okay,
so let's take a look. השביע עליהם חמשה פעמים. hishpia aleihem chamisha
pe'amim. מנלן דכפירה בבית דין הוא דמחייבי וחוץ לבית דין לא מחייבי?
menalan de'kfira be'Beis Din hu de'mechayvei ve'chutz le'Beis Din lo mechayvei? Where
do you see that you require that it's only the כפירה, kfira,
the denial, in בית דין Beis Din is what is when they
become obligated for the שבועה, shevua, not outside of בית דין? Beis
Din? So
אמר אביי אמר קרא, amar Abaye amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says,
אם לוא יגיד ונשא עונו. im lo yagid ve'nasa avono. If he
does not testify, he will bear the burden of his sin. לא
אמרתי לך אלא במקום שאילו מגיד זה מתחייב זה ממון. lo amarti
lach ela bemakom she'ilu magid ze mis'chayev ze mamon. So that means
that the place where this is taking place is a place where
him saying it right now is a place where the other person,
if the witnesses would actually give their testimony right now, that would
obligate the other person. So the fact that it says אם לוא
יגיד im lo yagid means where we are taking the denial is
taking place in a context where the הגדה hagada could take place.
It's taking place in a בית דין. Beis Din.
Okay, so אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav Papa le'Abaye,
so then Rav Papa said to Abaye the obvious question, אי הכי
אימא שבועה גופה בבית דין? i hachi eima shevua gufa be'Beis Din?
אין ושלא בבית דין לא. in ve'shelo be'Beis Din lo.
So if that's true, if the whole context of the פסוק, pasuk,
ושמעה קול אלה והוא עד או ראה או ידע אם לוא יגיד
ונשא עונו, ve'shama kol ala ve'hu eid o ra'a o yada im
lo yagid ve'nasa avono, so it starts with a שבועה. shevua. So
let's say even the taking the שבועה shevua has to happen in
בית דין Beis Din and any שבועה shevua outside of בית דין
Beis Din is not part of this פרשה parsha of שבועת העדות.
Shevuas Ha'eidus.
So לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka da'atach. No, that would not be
possible. Why? דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, beraisa, לאחת. le'achas.
Okay, the פסוק pasuk says, והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה ve'haya ki
yesham le'achas me'eila
at the end of the three cases that you're חייב chayav this
עולה ויורד oleh ve'yored for שבועת ביטוי Shevuas Bituy and שבועת העדות
Shevuas Ha'eidus and
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tum'as mikdash ve'kodashav. So it says if a person
is חייב chayav for one of these, which means the פשט pshat
of the פסוק pasuk is one of these three scenarios of a
קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh ve'yored. But the way we read it
is לחייב על כל אחת ואחת. lechayev al kol achas ve'achas. That
tells you that you could be חייב chayav multiple times for multiple
שבועות shevuos in one case. That's how we're learning it. Exactly the
case that we have in our משנה, mishna, you take five שבועות
shevuos outside of בית דין Beis Din and then you're כופר, kofer,
you're חייב chayav for all five שבועות. shevuos. Okay, so we know
that there's an idea that you could be חייב chayav multiple times.
And now let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. ואי סלקא דעתך
בבית דין מי מחייב על כל אחת ואחת? ve'i salka da'atach be'Beis
Din mi mechayev al kol achas ve'achas? But if we were to
assume that everything had to occur in בית דין, Beis Din, both
the שבועה shevua and the כפירה, kfira, then you could never get
multiple חיובים chiyuvim for one case. Why? Because והתנן השביע עליהם חמשה
פעמים. ve'hatnan hishpia aleihem chamisha pe'amim. חמישה פעמים בפני בית דין וכפרו
אין חייב אלא אחת. chamisha pe'amim bifnei beis din ve-kafru ein chayav
ela achas. אמר רבי שמעון
מה טעם הואיל ואינם יכולים לחזור ולהודות. amar Rabi Shimon ma taam
ho'il ve-einam yecholim lachazor u-lehodot. So because the next case of our
משנה mishnah tells us that if you took five oaths in בית
דין, beis din, you're only חייב chayav for the first one, because
after the first one, you're no longer able to testify, even if
you wanted to, so you're out of the category of שבועת העדות.
shvuas ha-edus. Your testimony, you're not even in a position to testify
after you do the first denial in בית דין. beis din. So
because we have a tradition that you could be חייב chayav for
multiple קרבנות korbanos for one case, and we assume that's a case
of שבועת העדות, shvuas ha-edus, then,
and we know that that could not work if you took multiple
שבועות shvuos in בית דין, beis din, because as soon as you
took your first one, you're out of the category of עדות. edus.
So the only way it could work is if you took multiple
שבועות shvuos outside of בית דין, beis din, where each שבועה shvua
is meaningful, because every moment you're still able to come and testify,
and maybe that שבועה shvua will get and motivate you to come
and testify. So that tells us that the שבועה shvua can happen,
and multiple שבועות, shvuos, if you're going to be חייב, chayav, have
to happen outside of בית דין. beis din. So what do you
do with אם לא יגיד im lo yagid to tell you that
the כפירה, kfira, the thing that will trigger it, the חיוב, chiyuv,
you know, that has to be in בית דין beis din and
the כפירה kfira outside of בית דין beis din does not trigger
it? Okay. אלא לאו שמע מינה שבועה חוץ לבית דין כפירה בבית
דין. ela lav shma mina shvua chutz la-beis din kfira be-beis din.
All right, so it's very interesting how we got to this and
certainly not from a simple reading of the פסוק, pasuk, but from
working backwards from the idea that there could be multiple חיובים. chiyuvim.
We have an idea of multiple חיובים chiyuvim and we have an
idea of it has to be in בית דין, beis din, and
the only way those two will work together is the multiple שבועות
shvuos outside of בית דין, beis din, but the כפירה kfira that
actually triggers the חיוב chiyuv is in בית דין. beis din. Okay,
now the other thing I should point out here is that you're
still making a שבועת שקר, shvuas sheker, right? If you say you
don't know testimony. Like all these cases where you're not חייב chayav
for שבועת העדות, shvuas ha-edus, כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד, keivan
she-higid shuv eino chozer u-magid, or five, you know, five שבועות shvuos
in בית דין, beis din, all those types of cases, it's still
a שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. All right, but that's a discussion the
גמרא gemara had earlier: Are you חייב שבועת ביטוי chayav shvuas bitui
when something is a שבועת העדות shvuas ha-edus that doesn't fit the
parameters of שבועת העדות? shvuas ha-edus? You might remember we had that
discussion, because you can't reverse it and make it apply to the
future, you can only make it apply to the past. So but
our focus is not whether there's any חיוב chiyuv on the other
שבועות, shvuos, but whether it falls into the category of שבועת העדות.
shvuas ha-edus. All right,
moving on. First wide line. כפרו שניהם כאחת חייבין. kafru shneihem ke-achas
chayavin. If they both simultaneously denied, then both of the עדים edim
have to be חייב chayav a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא gemara
says, האי אי אפשר לצמצם. hai ee efshar le-tzamtzem. So the גמרא
gemara says, you know,
it's impossible to ever say something happened literally simultaneously. So
what's the scenario? And if you can't figure out, you know, like
it'll always be one after the other, but if you don't know
exactly who was first, who was second, you know, you'll never know
who's חייב, chayav, or even if, you know, you're dead sure this
guy is first, the second guy couldn't have started at the exact
split second of the first guy, so the second guy will always
be פטור. patur. So the גמרא gemara says, אמר רב חסדה הא
מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא דאמר אפשר לצמצם. amar Rav Chisda ha
mani Rabi Yosi ha-Glili hi de-amar efshar le-tzamtzem. Well, there's a position
of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yosi ha-Glili that he says that when
things look like they're happening in the same time, okay, then we
actually assume, you know, we do the best as our human experience
allows us and we actually assume that they are, that it, that
they did happen exactly at the same time. So this is a
debate that comes up in בכורות bechoros where if you have a,
let's say a sheep that gave birth and it had never given
birth before and it gave birth to two, you know, to two
lambs at the same time, like twins, and they both came out
at the same time, do you treat, do you say one is
definitely the בכור, bechor, we just don't know which one, so each
is a ספק בכור, safek bechor, that would be what the חכמים
chachamim says, but רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yosi ha-Glili says that they're
both בכורות, bechoros, both of them came out first. So that's, so
yes, it's רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabi Yosi ha-Glili. Now there's a much
easier answer here: When we said the same time, we did not
have to mean literally the same time. So let's see what the
גמרא gemara says. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא רבנן. Rabi Yochanan amar
afilu teima rabanan. No, it could be even the rabbis that disagree
with רבי יוסי. Rabi Yosi. כגון שכפרו שניהם בתוך כדי דיבור ובתוך
כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי. kegon she-kafru shneihem be-soch k'dei dibur ve-soch k'dei
dibur ke-dibur dami. They did it within the, you know, within there's
a period in הלכה halacha that you're allowed to retract things, and
that might even just be considered also like the period in which
we say that things occurred in the same time. And that's בתוך
כדי דיבור, be-soch k'dei dibur, especially if we're dealing with a speech
act. And that's, oh, but not always. And that's like בתוך כדי
דיבור. be-soch k'dei dibur. So the amount of time it takes to
say a short utterance. The utterance is, you know, שאילת תלמיד לרב
she'ilas talmid le-rav or שאילת רב לתלמיד. she'ilas rav le-talmid. שאילת תלמיד
לרב she'ilas talmid le-rav is שלום עליך רבי, shalom alecha Rabi, you
know, and, you know,
and שאילת רב לתלמיד she'ilas rav le-talmid is just שלום עליך. shalom
alecha. So
and some say that the
שאילת תלמיד לרב she'ilas talmid le-rav is שלום עליך רבי ומורי, shalom
alecha Rabi u-mori, four words, but anyway רש"י Rashi here says it's
just שלום עליך רבי. shalom alecha Rabi. So let's take a look.
But that is But כתוך כדי דיבור ketokh kedei dibbur is often
used in speech acts about the time that like you can sort
of correct yourself, so even if you're even the principle of כיון
שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד, kivan shehigid shuv eino hozer umagid, you
can like you know sometimes people misspeak and you can correct yourself
if you within like the time it takes to say two or
three words, or three or four words I should say. But sometimes
the גמרא Gemara even uses it just in general as a way
of defining close enough to be considered at the same time. Classic
case of that would be that somebody hears, you know, his father
dies and he does קריעה, kria, and then תוך כדי דיבור toch
kedei dibbur he heard that his mother died, and we say that
the קריעה kria that he just did counts also for the death
of his mother, even though the thing that obligates the קריעה kria
is hearing about the death. So, but anyway, but תוך כדי דיבור
toch kedei dibbur is a general amount of time, certainly in speech
acts that things are considered to be overlapping and taking place within
the same amount of time. All right, so you don't have to
have it exactly at the same time.
So one even wonders why the גמרא Gemara even thought that they
had to be precisely, even without תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur,
one could imagine that the first עד eid said שבועה שאיני יודע
shvuah she'eini yode'a and the second one started overlapping at the you
know with the first one, but but anyway, but that's at least
what the גמרא Gemara says. כגון ששפו אפילו תימא רבנן כגון שכפרו
שניהם בתוך כדי דיבור. kegon sheshafu afilu teima Rabbanan kegon shekafru sheneihem
betoch kedei dibbur. בתוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי, betoch kedei dibbur kedibbur
dami, it's like it was all within the same type of time
of of speaking. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, amar leh Rav
Aha miDiphti leRavina, מכדי, michdi, one minute. How does this work? תוך
כדי דיבור כמה הוי כדי שאלת תלמיד לרב. toch kedei dibbur kamma
havei kedei she'eilas talmid lerav. Okay, it is the time it takes
for a you know תלמיד talmid to say hello to his רבי,
rebi, שלום עליך רבי shalom alecha rebi or רבי ומורי. rebi umori.
So if that's true, עד דאמר שבועה שאיני יודע לך עדות, ad
de'amar shvuah she'eini yode'a lach eidus, טובא הוה. tuva hava. So
he assumed that it had to be תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei
dibbur from the beginning of the guy's testimony. So the first guy
said שבועה שאיני יודע לך עדות shvuah she'eini yode'a lach eidus and
then the second guy started, well that would always have already been
more than תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur from the beginning speech
of the first person. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה כל
אחד ואחד תוך כדי דיבור של חברו. amar leh kol echad ve'echad
toch kedei dibbur shel chaveiro. No, no, no, you just have to
start within the תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur of your friend,
within the few you know from the time he finishes, you have
a few more seconds and if you start within those like one
second, that תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur time, it's like you're
speaking at the same time. Which also means that once you're saying
that, that they don't have to start at the same time, the
גמרא Gemara could have given the scenario also that they spoke at
the same time and overlapping. But okay, that's when they did it
both exactly or roughly at the same time, that they're both חייב.
chayav. בזה אחר זה ראשון חייב ושני פטור. bezeh achar zeh rishon
chayav vesheni patur. But if it was sequential, the first one is
חייב, chayav, but by the time you get to the second one,
he doesn't have, you know, testimony that can fully help the guy
because he's only an עד אחד, eid echad, so he would be
פטור. patur. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתניתין דלא כי האי תנא.
matnitin dila kehai tanna. Our משנה mishnah is not like the following
תנא, tanna, דתניא, detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braisa, משביע עד
אחד פטור. mashpia eid echad patur. If you do, you know, impose
a שבועה shvuah on an עד אחד, eid echad, you're פטור, patur,
which is obviously the assumption of our משנה. mishnah. But now we
find out רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון מחייב. Rebbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon mechayev.
Rebbe Eliezer ben Rebbe Shimon says no, he also has testimony that
could help, you know, maybe not do the whole thing, but it
could help, so you're also חייב. chayav. לימא בהא קמיפלגי. leima beha
kamipalgi.
So let's understand what is at the core of their debate. Maybe
this is what they're debating. דמר סבר עד אחד כי אתא לשבועה
הוא דקא אתא ומר סבר עד אחד כי אתא לממונא הוא דקא
אתא. demar savar eid echad ki ata lishvuah hu deka ata umar
savar eid echad ki ata lemamona hu deka ata. So this is
a beautiful conceptual question here. We all know that the הלכה halacha
is that an עד אחד, eid echad, if an עד אחד eid
echad says, you know, you ראובן Reuven owe שמעון Shimon a hundred
dollars, that that doesn't mean that the court now believes it and
takes the hundred dollars from ראובן Reuven and gives it to שמעון,
Shimon, but ראובן Reuven has to take a שבועה, shvuah, an עד
אחד eid echad is מחייב שבועה. mechayev shvuah. ראובן Reuven has to
take a שבועה shvuah that he doesn't owe שמעון Shimon a hundred
dollars. So the גמרא Gemara is asking conceptually what is going on
here. Is it the הלכה halacha that the testimony of an עד
eid is not really doesn't have the weight to be מוציא ממון,
motzi mamon, you know,
but it because it has to be counterbalanced, so you have to
make a שבועה shvuah to give backing to your claim to counterbalance
that of the עד, eid, but the only thing the עד eid
is מחייב mechayev is a שבועה. shvuah. Or do we say differently?
Do we say actually that an עד אחד eid echad can actually
be מחייב ממון? mechayev mamon? Okay, however, there's a חידוש chidush that
if it's only an עד אחד eid echad and you take a
שבועה shvuah that because of the weakness of the עד אחד eid
echad that neutralizes it and you don't have to pay ממון. mamon.
So is the עד אחד מחייב שבועה? eid echad mechayev shvuah? Fundamentally
he's only coming to say that, you know, his testimony demands an
opposite שבועה, shvuah, or is he fundamentally coming to be מוציא ממון
motzi mamon but your שבועה shvuah is strong enough to block it?
All right, and an obvious presumed נפקא מינה nafka mina about this
would be if you can't take the שבועה shvuah do you have
to pay? But that actually there is that הלכה, halacha, מתוך שאינו
יכול לישבע משלם. mitoch she'eino yachol lishava meshalem. But anyway the גמרא
Gemara is saying that this is conceptually maybe the debate. So if
you say fundamentally he's coming for ממון, mamon, so then that would
be relevant to the שבועת עדות, shvuas eidus, you know, just like
two witnesses, he's מחייב ממון, mechayev mamon, there's just an easier
way. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ותסברא *Vtisborah* does that really
make sense to say that that is the debate? אמר אביי Abaye,
*Amar Abaye* הכל
מודי באת סוטה Sotah *hakol modim
b'eit Sotah* והכל מודי בעד סוטה Sotah. *v'hakol modim b'eid Sotah* ומחלוקת
בעד סוטה Sotah *u'machlokes b'eid Sotah*.
Okay so that's a little you know
cryptic phrase but let's see what it means. הכל מודי באת סוטה
Sotah, *Hakol modim b'eit Sotah*. Everybody agrees when it comes to the
eit... to the one... the witness of a סוטה Sotah, *Sotah* והכל
מודי בעד שכנגדו Sheknegdo, חשוד על השבועה *v'hakol modim b'eid she'kenegdo chashud
al hashvua*. Excuse me I misread that. Let's do that again. אמר
אביי Abaye. הכל מודי באת סוטה והכל מודי בעד סוטה ומחלוקת בעד
סוטה *Amar Abaye hakol modim b'eit Sotah v'hakol modim b'eid Sotah u'machlokes
b'eid Sotah*. So this debate of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Eliezer
Berabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* and the חכמים Chachamim *v'hachachamim* אביי
Abaye *Abaye* says they would actually agree in one scenario when it
was an עד אחד Eid Echad, *eid echad* by סוטה *Sotah* and
they would actually agree in a different scenario when it was two
עדים Eidim, *eidim* by סוטה *Sotah* and they would disagree this same
מחלוקת *machlokes* of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Eliezer Berabbi Shimon *Rabbi
Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* and the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim* would disagree in a
third scenario of עד Eid סוטה *eid Sotah*. We're going to unpack
all of this in a bit and we're not done. הכל מודי
בעד אחד *Hakol modim b'eid echad* also רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi
Eliezer Berabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* and the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim*
would agree in a certain type of a case of עד אחד
Eid Echad *eid echad* והכל מודי בעד שכנגדו חשוד על השבועה *v'hakol
modim b'eid she'kenegdo chashud al hashvua*. And everybody will also agree in
a case of an עד אחד Eid Echad *eid echad* when the
other person the opposite person cannot take a שבועה Shvuah *shvua* the
person on whom the שבועה Shvuah. *shvua* is being placed is not
trustworthy and would not be allowed to take a שבועה Shvuah, *shvua*.
So that's a very nice cryptic statement and we're going to unpack
all of that but what we're going to see when we unpack
it is that at the core of their debate is not the
question of whether an עד אחד Eid Echad *eid echad* is coming
for שבועה Shvuah. *shvua* or ממון *mamon* but at the core of
their debate is whether דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי *davar hagarum l'mamon
k'mamon dami*. Since an עד אחד Eid Echad *eid echad* is coming
to obligate a שבועה Shvuah, *shvua* and most people won't take a
שבועה Shvuah. *shvua* this is the way רש"י *Rashi* says it or
at least there's a possibility he won't take a שבועה Shvuah. *shvua*
then רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says effectively this עד אחד Eid Echad
*eid echad* has the power to get the other guy to pay
and therefore even though he doesn't he's not מחייב mechayav *mechayev* the
person to pay since through his testimony it can bring about that
the other person will pay that's considered עדות edut *eidus* that will
that you know is for ממון *mamon* and therefore you're חייב Chayav
*chayav* in שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus. *shvuat ha'eidus*. And the חכמים Chachamim
*Chachamim* say no even if it will bring it about if the
עד Eid *eid* does not directly obligate ממון *mamon* then it is
not מחייב *mechayev* it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so
let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you're right. אלא Ela דכולי עלמא
עד אחד ed echad כי אתא לשבועה אתא *Ella d'chuli alma eid
echad ki ata l'shvua ata*. We can say that everybody says an
עד אחד ed echad *eid echad* is coming for שבועה Shvuah. *shvua*
and not coming for ממון *mamon*. That's not what the principle of
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* is based on. והכא
בהא קמיפלגי *V'hacha b'hai k'mifligi* this is what their debate is. מר
סבר דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי ומר סבר לאו כממון דמי *Mar
savar davar hagarum l'mamon k'mamon dami v'mar savar lav k'mamon dami*. רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* says since an עד אחד
ed echad *eid echad* will often most of the time can bring
about that the other guy will pay then therefore it's like the
עד אחד ed echad *eid echad* is מוציא ממון *motzi mamon* you
know and therefore חייב Chayav. *chayav* for שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus. *shvuat
ha'eidus*. It's עדות *eidus* that could lead that could bring about money
being paid. And the חכמים *Chachamim* say no if that does not
mean directly it is obligating money and therefore it is not חייב
Chayav *chayav* for שבועת העדות shevuat ha'edut *shvuat ha'eidus*. Okay and now
we get to unpack this very cryptic statement of אביי *Abaye*. גופא
*Gufa* let's look at what אביי *Abaye* said. אמר אביי הכל מודי
באת סוטה והכל מודי בעד סוטה ומחלוקת בעד סוטה הכל מודי בעד
אחד והכל מודי בעד שכנגדו חשוד על השבועה *Amar Abaye hakol modim
b'eit sotah v'hakol modim b'eid sotah umachlokes b'eid sotah hakol modim b'eid
echad v'hakol modim b'eid she'kenegdo chashud al hashvua*. So now we just
repeated the whole thing. Now we're going to unpack it. הכל מודי
באת סוטה *Hakol modim b'eit Sotah* שחייב *she'chayav* בעד טומאה *b'eid tumah*
דרחמנא הימניה *d'rachmana heimnei*. Okay so if one after the way a
סוטה *Sotah* works is a husband tells his wife he suspects her
of adultery don't be in private with this man and then she
goes ahead and and there has to be two witnesses to that
warning and then if she goes ahead and is private with that
man and there's a witness that sees that she's in private she
went into a private secluded space with that man then you go
through the whole סוטה *Sotah* ritual. But let's say there's actually a
witness that testifies after this whole thing the warning and going in
private testifies that he actually saw them have sex. So then you
know the הלכה Halacha? *halacha* is is that then it is assumed
that she then you accept that testimony not in the sense of
the punishment of adultery of execution but in the sense that then
she gets divorced and loses her כתובה Kesuvah. *ketubah*. Okay so that
we learn out by עד אחד ed echad *eid echad* that an
עד ed? טומאה *eid tumah* an עד ed *eid* that actually says
he saw the sex occur is believed. So everybody would agree that
if you had an עד ed טומאה *eid tumah* and you were
משביע *mashpia* an עד טומאה *eid tumah* to come and testify and
he denied it that you would and he was lying that he
would be חייב Chayav. *chayav* why? Because that his testimony will be
accounted like two witnesses not again for the punishment of adultery but
for two witnesses for the monetary consequence that she loses her כתובה
Kesuvah. *ketubah* and that's what you need the monetary consequence to be
חייב Chayav *chayav* in שבועת העדות *shvuat ha'eidus*.
So that's everybody agrees in the עד *eid* of סוטה *Sotah* the
עד *eid* of טומאה *tumah* that she had that she had sex.
רחמנא הימניה that the Torah believed him, דכתיב Dichsiv ועד אין בה—quote
V'eid Ein Bah יש בה. Yesh Bah. So from "there was no
witness against her," any witness, even an עד אחד, ed echad even
though often we interpret the word עד to mean two עדים, is
believed for the monetary consequence that she gets divorced without her כתובה.
Kesuvah. So that's a type of an עד אחד ed echad, that
has direct monetary consequence, everybody agrees. והכל מודים בעדי סוטה שפטור, V'hacol
Modim B'eidei Sotah Shepatur, and in the flip, there'll be a case
of even two witnesses that everybody would agree that you're not חייב
chayav for even if they're lying for שבועת העדות. What is that?
בעדי קינוי דהוה גורם דגורם, B'eidei Kinuy Dehava Gorem D'gorem, when it
is the witnesses where the husband warned her, "Do not go into
private with that man." So that case, even if, you know, you
would need multiple steps to get to the monetary consequence. You know,
she—first the witnesses testify, you know, that the warning happened, then she
went into private and there was a witness to that, right? So
that is like, you know, and then, you know, even there, depending
on what's going to happen with the סוטה ritual, you know, either
she will or won't lose her כתובה. Kesuvah. So that is three,
you know, that's not just it can cause money, it's cause-it-can-lead to
something that can lead to something that can cause money. So everybody
would agree that that's too far removed, that it's not considered עדי
ממון Eidei Mamon even for רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Top of ל"ב
עמוד ב', Lamed Bais Amud Bais, ומחלוקת בעדי סוטה, U'machlokes B'eidei Sotah,
and and there debate of עד אחד ed echad, would play out
in another case of witnesses by a סוטה. Which case? בעדי סתירה,
B'eidei Stirah, the witnesses or the witness, the, you know, the עד
אחד ed echad, that she went into private with this man. And
notice that the גמרא Gemara, here even says בעדי B'eidei in the
plural. There's a whole question whether you need two witnesses or one
witness that she went in private with this man. But here, even
if it were two witnesses, the חכמים would still say that you're
פטור Patur and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון would say you're חייב. chayav
Why? Because מר סבר דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי וחייב ומר סבר
לאו כממון דמי Mar Savar Davar Ha'gorem L'mamon K'mamon Dami V'chayav U'mar
Savar Lav K'mamon Dami because even in a case here of two
witnesses, it's not directly saying that she loses her כתובה. ketubah. It
then has to result, you know, the next step is that she
goes ahead and she refuses to drink the סוטה water, you know,
and then she loses her כתובה. So for the חכמים, it is
still not directly have consequence-monetary consequence even though it's two witnesses. And
for רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, since it will—could indirectly lead to monetary
consequence, you are חייב for שבועת העדות. Okay, so that was very
cute. Within the case of סוטה, you have one case which is
debated, one case everybody agrees that they're פטור, Patur, one case everybody
agrees that you're חייב.
Moving on.
והכל מודים בשכנגדו חשוד על השבועה, V'hacol Modim Besheknegdo Chashud Al Hashvuah,
and והכל מודים בעד אחד דרבי אבא. V'hacol Modim B'eid Echad D'Rebbi
Abba. And everybody agrees when the guy who has the obligation to
take the שבועה Shvuah can't make it, and everybody agrees in a
case of עד אחד ed echad, with the and then we'll see
that that will be like the scenario like a case of רבי
אבא Rebbi Abba which we'll quote in a minute. So now we're
going to unpack this. הכל מודים בשכנגדו חשוד על השבועה Hacol Modim
Besheknegdo Chashud Al Hashvuah so where the opposite party is is suspect
for swearing falsely based on past behavior and therefore is not allowed
to take the שבועה. Shvuah So the language שכנגדו, the opposite guy,
is חשיד, Chashid, is suspect, is not clear who we're talking about.
So the גמרא wants to clarify it. דחשיד מאן? D'chashid Man? Who
exactly is suspect? אילימא דחשיד לווה, Eilima D'chashid Loveh, the guy who
borrowed the money. So דאמר ליה מלווה אי אתית אסהדת לי
הוה משתבענא ושקילנא. D'amar Lei Malveh Ei Asis Ashedis Li Hava Mishtabana
V'shakilna.
So so if it's that what we assume, that the person who
has to take the שבועה, shevuah the לווה, Loveh, the person who
borrowed the money or the claim is borrowed the money, is not
trusted to make a
שבועה. shevuah. So אילימא דחשיד לווה, Eilima D'chashid Loveh, דאמר ליה מלווה,
D'amar Lei Malveh, and therefore the creditor is now saying to this
witness who is denying that he has testimony and could obligate the
לווה Loveh to make a שבועה, shevuah so what is he saying
to this witness? He's saying, אי אתית אסהדת לי, Ei Asis Ashedis
Li, if you would have come testify on my behalf, so what
would have been the הלכה? Halacha The לווה Loveh would have been
obligated in a שבועה. shevuah But the לווה Loveh because עד אחד
obligates a שבועה. shevuah, But the לווה Loveh is not trusted to
make a שבועה. shevuah So we're going to learn in a later
פרק Perek that the הלכה halacha? is when that happens, it becomes—the
שבועה shevuah gets put on the מלווה Malveh and now the מלווה
Malveh can take the שבועה shevuah that what he's saying is true
and then win his case. So he's saying, if you would have
come and testified on my behalf, הוה משתבענא ושקילנא, Hava Mishtabana V'shakilna,
I would have taken an oath and I would have won the
case. So the גמרא says no, ולימא ליה, V'lima Lei, but let
him say-but let the עד say back to the מלווה, Malveh, מי
יימר דמשתבעת? Mi Yeimar D'mishtabas? Who who would have said you would
have taken the oath? Maybe you would have refused to take the
oath? Again, my testimony would not directly have led to winning the
case. And according to the חכמים, you're only חייב if the testimony
would have directly led to winning the case. And here there's another
stage in the process. the מלווה Malve would have had to make
a שבועה shevuah since the לווה Loveh cannot. אלא says the גמרא,
כגון ששניהם חשודים. kegon she'shneihem chashudim. Okay, so fine, both the מלווה
Malve and the לווה Loveh are suspect. Neither of them are trusted
to make a שבועה. shevuah And in that case, the שבועה shevuah
starts on the לווה, Loveh, he can't make it. We would have
transferred it to the מלווה, Malve, he can't make it. So what's
the הלכה? halacha So דאמר מר, de'amar mar, חזרה שבועה למחויב לה,
chazrah shevuah le'mechuyav lah, that the שבועה shevuah goes back to the
לווה Loveh which is where it starts, ומתוך שאינו יכול להישבע משלם,
umitoch she'eino yachol lehishava meshalem, and since he can't take the שבועה,
shevuah he has to pay up. Okay, so everybody would agree in
a scenario where the עד אחד is מחייב a שבועה shevuah but
no שבועה shevuah, can be made, so that חיוב שבועה chiyuv shevuah
would translate directly into a חיוב ממון. chiyuv mamon. So in that
case, everybody agrees that the עד אחד is חייב שבועת העדות chayav
shevuat ha'edut because his עדות would have directly had the effect of
paying out the debt. Okay, and last case of אביי, הכל מודי
בעד אחד דרבי אבא. hakol modei be'ed echad de'Rabbi Abba. Everybody would
also agree in the case of the עד אחד of רבי אבא.
Rabbi Abba. What was the case of the עד אחד of רבי
אבא? Rabbi Abba? דההוא גברא דחטף נסקא מחבריה. de'hahu gavra de'chataf naska
me'chaverei. A certain person grabbed like a chunk of metal from his
friend.
אתא לקמיה דרבי אמי ata lekamei de'Rabbi Ami and
they came in front of רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. הוה יתיב רבי
אבא קמיה hava yativ Rabbi Abba kamei and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
was there sitting in the בית מדרש beit midrash or in the
בית דין. beit din. אזל אייתי חד סהדא דמיחטף חטפא מיניה. azal
ayiti chad sahada demichataf chatafa minei. So the person who had the
chunk of silver or metal grabbed from him brought an עד אחד
that this guy came into my house, grabbed this chunk of silver
from me. אמר ליה, amar leh, so the guy who grabbed it
then said, אין, in, it's true, חטפי, chatafi, I did grab it,
ודידי חטפי, vedidi chatafi, but it was mine, I was just taking
back what was mine. Now normally you're not believed to go into
somebody's house and take something and say it's yours, right? That type
of a thing would not normally be believed. So let's see how
this is going to play out. אמר רבי אמי, amar Rabbi Ami,
so said רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, היכי דייני דייני להאי דינא, heichi
dayni daynei lehai dina, how should a judge judge this case?
לישלם, lishalem, should you say that this guy has to pay it
back? ליכא תרי סהדי, leika terei sahadei, so there's not two witnesses.
ליפטריה, lifterei, should we let him get off the hook? איכא חד
סהדא, ika chad sahada, there's one witness. Okay, what's the normal הלכה
halacha of one witness? איכא חד סהדא דמיחטף חטף, ika chad sahada
demichataf chataf, that he grabbed it. לישתבע, lishtava, so let him take
an oath, that's what one witness normally obligates. כיון דאמר אין חטפי
ודידי חטפי, keivan de'amar in chatafi vedidi chatafi, since he acknowledges that
he took it and he just says he took his own thing,
so
הוה ליה כגזלן, hava leh kegazlan, he's like a גזלן. gazlan. Now
that's a phrase that's a little harsh, he's like a גזלן. gazlan.
Does it mean because he grabbed it he's like a גזלן? gazlan?
רש״י Rashi says it means he's like a גזלן gazlan for our
purposes. He's not able to take the שבועה shevuah that the תורה
Torah obligates him. So here's a case, the שבועה shevuah the תורה
Torah obligates him to take is "I didn't grab it", the שבועה
shevuah that contradicts what the עד אחד says. He's not able to
take that, he acknowledges he did grab it. So what do you
do with a case where he can't make the שבועה shevuah that
the תורה Torah obligates, but he would be willing to make a
שבועה to give an explanation that would effectively neutralize the testimony of
the עד? Does he get to make that שבועה or do we
say sorry, you're obligated to make a שבועה that you can't take
and you have to pay? So that's the question. אמר
ליה רבי אבא, amar leh Rabbi Abba, so רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
said, הוה ליה מחויב שבועה ואינו יכול לישבע, hava leh mechuyav shevuah
ve'eino yachol lehishava, וכל המחויב שבועה ואינו יכול לישבע משלם. vechol hamichuyav
shevuah ve'eino yachol lehishava meshalem. It's very nice that he has an
explanation, but right now he has an obligation to make a שבועה,
he's not able to make the שבועה to contradict the עד because
he acknowledged he took it. So if you have an obligation to
make a שבועה and you can't do it, then the הלכה halacha
is that you have to pay. Okay, so this would be a
case where there would be an עד אחד, but because of the
circumstances, similar to the case of when neither of them were trustworthy,
so there was no שבועה on the table, so here as well
there's an עד אחד, but because of the circumstances, the שבועה is
not what's going to happen. What's going to happen is he's going
to have to pay. Okay, so now we move on to רב
פפא Rav Papa making a similar statement to אביי. אמר רב פפא
הכל מודי במיתה שהוא חייב והכל מודי במיתה שהוא פטור. amar Rav
Papa hakol modei bemitah shehu chayav vehakol modei bemitah shehu patur. Every,
same way אביי did it with סוטה, רב פפא Rav Papa says
this debate of the חכמים and רבי אליעזר בן שמעון, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Shimon, I can give you a scenario where there's one עד
about the death of a woman's husband where everybody would agree that
he's חייב for שבועת העדות if he's lying and there's a case
where everybody would agree that he's פטור. patur. So the basic הלכה
is that, you know, in certain cases where the husband went off
to sea and there's no testimony to be had, two witnesses about
what happened to him,
חז״ל Chazal were willing to believe even an עד אחד, even עד
מפי עד, ed mipi ed, that the woman's husband had died to
allow her to get remarried that she should not be left an
עגונה. agunah. And that also has monetary consequences because it allows her
to collect her כתובה. So רב פפא Rav Papa is saying that
with this עד אחד, there's a circumstances that everybody agrees he's חייב
and circumstances that everybody agrees he's פטור. patur. Let's take a look.
הכל מודים דפטור *hakol modim d'pator* הכל מודים בסיפא דפטור *hakol
modim b'seifa
d'pator*. Let's start with the second case when everybody agrees that he
would be exempt. דאמר לה לדידה ולא אמר להו לבי דינא *d'amar
la l'didah v'lo amar lehu l'vei dina* that he told the woman
that her husband died, but then when it came to בית דין
*beis din* he refused to testify and he took a שבועה *shvua*
in בית דין *beis din*. In that case, even though he swore
falsely in בית דין *beis din*, it doesn't matter because his testimony
was no longer needed once he had told the woman. דתנן *d'tnan*
האשה שאמרה מת בעלי תנשא מת בעלי תייבם *ha'isha she'amra meis ba'ali
tinasei meis ba'ali teiyavem*. If a woman says that my husband died,
then she can get remarried or she can get יבום *yibum* and
even if she only knows about it through an עד אחד *ed
echad*. Once he was willing to tell her, even though when it
came to בית דין *beis din* he refused to repeat what he
had said, it doesn't matter. Once she knew through him, his עדות
*eidus* at this point is no longer necessary.
That's a case everybody says he's פטור *pator*. והכל מודים בהיכא דחייב
*v'hakol modim b'heicha
d'chayav* and everybody also agrees that there's a case where according to
both opinions he'd be חייב *chayav*. דלא אמר לה לדידה ולא אמר
להו לבי דינא *d'lo amar la l'didah v'lo amar lehu l'vei dina*.
He both refused to tell her and he refused to tell בית
דין *beis din* and in that case, even though if he would
have said either to her or to בית דין *beis din*, then
she could have gotten remarried, she could have collected. Like the עד
אחד *ed echad* בסוטה *b'sotah* when he says that the woman had
had sex with this man, that there's a belief of an עד
אחד *ed echad* that has immediate monetary consequences. Here also by an
עד אחד *ed echad* that the husband died, immediate monetary consequences if
he is refusing to tell both her and the בית דין *beis
din*. Therefore everybody would agree in this case that he is חייב
*chayav*. Now the גמרא *gemara* just ends with one last sentence: שמע
מינה משביע עדי קרקע חייב *shma mina mashbia edei karka chayav*. One
minute, if we're talking here about the issue about her כתובה *kesubah*
and her כתובה *kesubah* has liens on land, then the monetary consequence
relates to something relating
to collecting from property and liens and that's קרקע *karka*. That's related
and the normal הלכה *halacha* is that you don't have a שבועה
*shvua* on קרקע *karka*. Can we infer from here that you would
have a שבועה *shvua* on something that had liens on land? The
גמרא *gemara* says no. דילמא דתפיסה מטלטלי *dilma d'tfisa metaltalei*. Maybe in
this case he had given her she was holding on to chattel.
Maybe he had put the כתובה *kesubah* in escrow and it was
not a case where she would have collected her כתובה *kesubah* from
land so you cannot bring any proof here relating to the idea
of a שבועה *shvua* when there are liens on land. We will
end here for now.